<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>This vvorlds folly Or A warning-peece discharged vpon the wickednesse thereof. By I.H.</title>
            <author>I. H., fl. 1615.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1615</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 56 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A02438</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 12570</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S103576</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99839327</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99839327</idno>
            <idno type="VID">3736</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A02438)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3736)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1103:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>This vvorlds folly Or A warning-peece discharged vpon the wickednesse thereof. By I.H.</title>
                  <author>I. H., fl. 1615.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[40] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by William Iaggard for Nicholas Bourne, and are to bee sold at his shop at the south entry of the Royal Exchange,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1615.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴ (A2 + *² ) B-D⁴ E² .</note>
                  <note>The first leaf is blank except for signature-mark "A".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:3736:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3736:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3736:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3736:2"/>
            <p>THIS Worlds Folly. OR A Warning-Peece diſcharged vpon the Wickedneſſe thereof.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Hor. Sat. 3. Lib. I.</bibl>
               <l>Et qui nocturnus divûm ſacra legerit; adſit</l>
               <l>Regula, peccatis qua poenas irroget aquas.</l>
            </q>
            <p>By I. H.</p>
            <figure>
               <p>HEB DDIM HEB DDIEV</p>
            </figure>
            <p>London Printed by William Iaggard for Nicholas Bourne, and are to bee ſold at his ſhop at the South entry of the Royal Exchange. 1615.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:3736:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3736:3"/>
            <head>To the more iudicious <hi>Reader.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Ot to affront a little structure with too large a Portall; briefly, let me thus far inſinuate my ſelfe into thy fauourable acceptance: That without ſquint-eye, thou wilt ſuprauiſe this my haſty, and artleſſe home-ſpun <hi>web,</hi> (the rapted Corrolarie of my more buſie howers) and ſilently ſuſpend thy Cryticke cenſure; ſeeing it was (from th' <hi>Exordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um</hi> to th' <hi>Exodium</hi>) warpt and wouen in ſome few ſad minuts, ſoftly stolne from the humide boſome of the ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Night, and ſuddenly endured the pittifull payne of Preſsing, without my knowledge or peruſall: and the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther I wooe thee hereunto, for that the intercedency of more waighty occurrences (from whence my ſhallow <hi>ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vulets</hi> of life draw head and yſſue) thwarts and repelles the deeper <hi>current</hi> of my more ſtudious diſſeignes. What errors therefore are obuious, either of commiſsion or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsion, rather attribute them to the <hi>Times</hi> breuity, then the <hi>Authors</hi> fatuity; albeit, the ſubſequent matter in part, be out of my garbe and element; who is (being most vnworthy) neither approu'd nor profes'd Diuine.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:3736:4"/>
            <head>Praecedentis Contractio.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>N quiſpiam (quaeſo) eſt, qui ſi iusta lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce illarii regionum vitia &amp; noeuos tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinet, in quibus Euangelij profeſsio floret ac viget, non ad ipſum penè peccat: api<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cem aſcendiſſe illas &amp; cuectas eſſe dicat. Si vnd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> circumſpiciat, ſi nobiles, infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mos, opulentos, egenos, eruditos, imperatos ob oculos ponat, ſingulos deforme: &amp; prodig oſos ſuae libidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis foetus parere &amp; parturire, non animo fingens concipiet, ſed reipſa id probans experietur. Si aulicae vitae primò te ſpecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latorem conſtituas, anlicorum luxum &amp; del cias, ſat ſcio, criminaberis: omnes ibi ſplendido veſtitu &amp; peregr no amic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tu volitant, nitidè compti, concinnè et molliter compoſit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulant, in Gallos, Italos, tanquam noua induta forma tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutati incedunt, qui mollitiem pluſquam muliebrem nimium effoeminata imitatione exprimunt: Iſto ferè nomine à Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheta ol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m taxati Iſraeliti ſunt,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Amos.</hi> 6.6.</note> 
               <hi>Accumbunt</hi> (inquit) <hi>in lec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis eburneis, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bunt in crateribus vini, &amp; praeſtantiſsimo vnguento vngunt ſe, neque afficiuntur aegritudine prop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter confractionem Ioſephi:</hi> Si ad ruſticam vitam contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plandam deſcendas ibi ſordida omnia &amp; agreſtia occurrent: inter ruſticos fraudem, dolum, auaritiam dominari, at<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> ara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trum ipſum comitari conſpicies: Iſtòs Propheta ſic increpat: <hi>Dicunt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Amos</hi> 8.4.</note> 
               <hi>quando tranſiuerit hoc nouilunium vel Sabba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum, vt vendamus comeatum, &amp; apperiamus frumenti horrea, minuendo Epſa, &amp; maius facie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>do pondus ac per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertendo lancibus doloſis.</hi> Si ad diuites te conuertas, il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis foenerandi, &amp; quacun<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> iniuria opes congerendi &amp; cumu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landi cupidinem amicam admodum &amp; familiarem eſſe tibi compertum erit: In quos ſic denunciat Eſaias: <hi>Vae coniun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gentibus domum domui,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 5 8.9.</note> 
               <hi>agrum agro adhibentibus, &amp;c.
<pb facs="tcp:3736:4"/>domus veſtrae deſolationicrunt (iurauit Deus) magnae &amp; p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aeſtantes.</hi> Si panperum tecta intrare digneris, &amp; cor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ns moribus te aſſuefeceris, nihil praeter querelas, turgia, vociſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rationes andias fu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> etiam rapinas, inimicitias deprehendes: de qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hus vere prae<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>xit vates: <hi>Ne creditore amico, ab <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a, quae cubat in ſinu tuo, obſerua fores oris tui.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Micah.</hi> 7.5</note> 
               <hi>Nam filius turpitudine afficit patre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, filia inſurgit in matre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuam, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus in ſocrum ſuam, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>inuci cuiuſque ſunt domeſtici ipſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us.</hi> Si doctorum &amp; literatorum claſſem ſpeculari cupias, legiſperitos nummorum plus, quam turis ſtudioſos, auaritiae magis quàm iuſtitiae min ſtrosdices: ne<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> hic ſilet idem Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheta, ita in Iudices innectus: <hi>Vtmalefaciant ambae ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus ſtrenue, Princeps poſcit et Iudex pro retributione,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Micah</hi> 7.3.</note> 
               <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Theologos praetereà oſc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tanter victitantes, multos gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gem non paſcentes quippe quod pluribus praeficiantur, vel in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eptiad docendum ſint, ſed in decimis tamen ſuis colligendis mirè aſtutos &amp; prouidos reperies: De quibus Zachariam ſic loquentem audiamus: <hi>Oues erraticas non viſitant,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Zach.</hi> 11</note> 
               <hi>aetate teneras non requirunt, et fractas non curant, ſed carnem pinguioris comedunt, et vngulas earum perrumpunt.</hi> Si poſtremò imperitam &amp; rudem plebeculam adeas, monſtritibi &amp; prod gi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> loco erit, ſi reſciueris, quàm rudis ea <hi>ſacrarum li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terarum ſit</hi> quàm <hi>diuini cultus</hi> ignara, quàm porrò verſata &amp; petulans, quàm ad iniurias proclouis, ad rixas parata, ad p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>etatis edendos fructus indocilis &amp; infrugifera: vt olim Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remias de populo conquestus eſt: <hi>A minimo corum vſque ad maximum, quiſquis eſt, de ditus eſt quaeſturi,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ierem.</hi> 13.</note> 
               <hi>etiam</hi> à <hi>Propheta vſque ad Sacerdotem, quiſquis eſt, agit falſò:</hi> Quis ergo eſt, qui isto modo per corruptos temporum noſtroru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> mores animo diſcurrens, poenam illam grauem &amp; acerbam praeſag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re non poſsit, quam nobis minatur Ichouah, niſt diuinae vindictae curſus noſtra pietate ſiſtatur?</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:3736:5"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3736:5"/>
            <head>This worlds a Foole. OR A warning-peece diſcharg'd vpon the wickedneſſe thereof.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen I but ſeriouſly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider this beſotted World, how (like a turbulent torrent) it is inundate with all ſorts of execrable ſinnes, a trembling horror vnties my bodies Liga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, my very knees beate to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether; and I could vnfainedly wiſh my ſinewie Structure to be transformed into a lumpe of Snow, that the ardor of my ſoules vexation might diſſolue it into penitentiall teares. Do not men act ſin with an auaritious appetite? Are not all varieties of abho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations lifted to their verticke point? Is not Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than, that ſubtile Impoſtor, put to his <hi>Nil vltra</hi> in coyning them, ſo faſt, as men would willingly put them in practiſe? Did <hi>Pride</hi> euer ſo ſtrut it vpon the Tiptoes as now it doth? Doth not Sir <hi>Iaques-Scabd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hams</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:3736:6"/>(ſole heire to ſome driueling and gowty Vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer, who to gaine one ſingle deniere to the number of multiplication, would ſucke Figges out of an Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes fundament) beſtow more on a paire of ſpangled Shoo-tyers, then ſome of our ancient Kings haue done of a whole garment? But
<q>Olim haec meminiſſe, nocebit.</q>
Can the diuell out of his ſhop of <hi>Faſhions,</hi> lay open more anticklike Formes then are forged on the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vile of mans fantaſticke Inuention? In Court, the <hi>Nobility</hi> are hardly diſtinguiſht from their <hi>followers:</hi> in City, the <hi>Merchant</hi> is not known from his <hi>Factor:</hi> in Country, the <hi>Gentry</hi> cannot be deſcried or deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed from the Bacon-eating, brawny-handed <hi>Ruſtick:</hi> and in generall, the Body-publicke is ſo ore-ſpredde with the leproſie of that gariſh Strumpet, PRIDE, as there is ſcarſe any difference betwixt Counteſſe and Curtezan, Lady and Chamber-maid, Miſtreſſe and greaſie Kitchin-wench, Gentleman and Mecha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicke; as for Knight and Taylor, there goes but a paire of Sheares betwixt them. How many miſpend and profuſely lauiſh their forenoones houres in the curious pranking of their ſinne-polluted bodies, but how few reſcrue one poore brace of minutes where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in to prouide ſpirituall induments to houſe their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked ſinfull ſoules? Neuer was that Apoththegme of old <hi>Bias</hi> the Philoſopher more verified <hi>(Omnia mea mecum porto)</hi> then in theſe our franticke Times: moſt men carry their wealth about with them, (not as <hi>Bias</hi> did, in Learning and Vertue) but vpon their backes in gorgeous apparrell: women do ſo commonly ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phiſticate
<pb facs="tcp:3736:6"/>their beauties, that one (though <hi>Linceus</hi>-ſighted) can hardly iudge whether they poſſeſſe their owne faces or no: and which is more then moſt la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentabl, euery ſnowy-headed Matron, euery tooth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe<note n="*" place="margin">An abuſe much com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaind of by the Company of <hi>Painters.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Mumpſimus,</hi> that one may ſee the ſunne go to bed through the furrowes of her forehead, muſt haue her boxe of odoriferous <hi>pomatum,</hi> and glittering <hi>Stybium</hi> wherewithall to parget, white-lime, and complexionate her rumpled cheekes, till ſhee looke as ſmug as an handſome painted cloſe-ſtoole or rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten poſt. But as for thoſe that lap vp their bodyes in the pleaſant miſts of aromaticke perfumes, let them withall ſwallow the Poets pill:
<q>
                  <l>Neuole, nonbenè olet, qui benè ſemper olet.<note place="margin">Martial.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Within a ſweete and Ciuet-lurking body, often is impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned a loathſome ſtinking ſoule.</l>
               </q>
               <hi>Murther</hi> is accounted but <hi>Manly reuenge,</hi> &amp; the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperate ſtabber cares no more to kill a man then to cracke a Flea. <hi>Vſury</hi> and <hi>Extortion</hi> are held <hi>Laudable vocations; Couetouſneſſe</hi> is ſtyled <hi>Thrift; Luxurie</hi> and <hi>Whoredome</hi> are reputed but <hi>youthfull trickes.</hi> And as for <hi>Drunkenneſſe,</hi> why that's a <hi>tolerable recreation:</hi> do not men purſue it with ſuch inordinat affection, that they oft neglect their functions, bid farewell to that domeſticke care they ought to entertaine, diſlodge that humane prouidence which ſhould be ſhut vp in the cabinet of their reaſonable <hi>part,</hi> and ſoly proſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute themſelues to quotidian carowſing, till their breathes ſmell no ſweeter then a Brewers Aperne? whilſt their families are wrung and grip't in the clut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of Pouerty, lockt vp and impriſoned from thoſe
<pb facs="tcp:3736:7"/>neceſſary ſupplements, which ſhoulde keepe both breath and body together at vnion. This is a wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy<note n="*" place="margin">S. Gregory.</note> Fathers opinion, <hi>That a manpoſſeſſed with a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell may be thought to be in a more hopefull state then a Drunkard: for albeit he be poſſeſſed, yet is it compulſiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and against his will; but the Drunkard wholly adopts and dedicates himſelfe with all the powerfull faculties of his ſoule, voluntarily to the ſeruice of Sathan.</hi> S. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine</hi> likewiſe deſcries three fearefull properties in a Drunkard:<note place="margin">S. Auguſtine.</note> 
               <hi>It confoundes Nature,</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>loſeth Grace, and conſequently incurres Gods wrathfull indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation to be powred out vpon the embracer thereof.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Swearing</hi> and blaſpheming Gods great and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious name, is reckoned for a <hi>Moral vertue,</hi> the <hi>grace of Birth</hi> and <hi>Honor,</hi> the <hi>cogniſance of an high-bred ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit.</hi> VVhat Chriſtian can refrain (that hath any ſpark of diuine intellect in him) to vnſluce the flood-gates of his eyes, and let his melting heart guſh through in teares, when in the ſtreets he ſhal heare litle children ſcarſe able to go, or ſpeake to be vnderſtood, volley forth moſt fearefull oathes, and vvith ſuch procliui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, as if they had bin tutor'd in their mothers womb? whilſt their parents ſtanding by, offer not to checke them vvith ſo much as a ſovvre reproofe, but ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing rather rather to ſolace themſelues in their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drens ſinnes, and delight in their owne damnations, like thoſe who die of a Sardinian laughter. If the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Law of <hi>Ludouicus</hi> were put in practiſe, (who hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring one ſweare, ſeared vp his lips with an hot yron) ſcarſe ten in as many pariſhes, but would bee glad to be in league with the Apothecaries Lip-ſalue. How
<pb facs="tcp:3736:7"/>many miraculous iudgements hath God ſhot out againſt the blaſphemers of his ſacred Name? (whoſe inſtances would be too prolixious:) what ſin can be more damnable, and yet what more practiſed? none can ſooner plu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge the ſoule into the implacable gulfe of perdition, and yet no ſin (by intentiue indeauour) ſo eaſie to be cropt off, and weeded vp; for that it is no incidentall iſſue of natural corruption, but an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidentall Monſter ingendred of corrupted cuſtome. A learned<note n="*" place="margin">Auguſt.</note> Father confeſſeth, That at euery other word, hee once vſed to ſweare, but at length endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoring to locke vp the doore of his lips, to ſet watch before his tongue, imploring diuine aſsiſtance ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, and intreating moreouer his friends to ſmite him with the rod of reprehenſion; in forty daies, hee vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly loſt the abuſiue vſe thereof: ſo that now (ſayth hee) <hi>Nihil mihi facilius, quàm non iurare,</hi> Nothing is more eaſie vnto mee then not to ſweare at all.<note n="*" place="margin">French In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentory.</note> It is recorded, that <hi>Lewis</hi> the 7. King of <hi>France</hi> divulged an Edict, that whoſoeuer was known to war againſt heauen with oathes, ſhould bee branded in the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head as a Capitall offender: ſhould not then euery Chriſtian labor to ſet a watch before his mouth and keepe the doore of his lips, that no rebellious words ſalley forth againſt his Creator? if not for the fear of temporall Iuſtice, yet leſt the God of Iuſtice ſhould brand his ſoule with the dreadfull ſtigme of eternall damnation, which no ſalue can heale, <hi>Haliacmons</hi> floud waſh out, nor length of time weare off.</p>
            <p>O lamentable! when the Turkes and Ethnicks out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrip vs in their cloudy and ignorant zeale: they will diſpute in the heart of their higheſt ſtreetes about
<pb facs="tcp:3736:8"/>their <hi>Alcoran</hi> and <hi>Mahometiſh</hi> Religion, with holy in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended deuotion: But what voice is heard in our ſtreetes? Nought but the ſqueaking out of thoſe<note n="a" place="margin">Laſciui contus quibuſ Satyri gaudent. Achan var. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſt. gen.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, obſcaene and light ligges, ſtuft with loath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome and vnheard-of Ribauldry, ſuckt from the poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonous dugs of Sinne-ſweld Theaters; controuerſall conferences about richeſt Beere, neateſt Wine, or ſtrongeſt Tobacco, wherein to drowne their ſoules, and draw meager diſeaſes vppon their diſtempered bodies. Therefore let them bee patient, if I rippe vp their impoſtumd'd vlcers (as<note n="b" place="margin">Eraſm. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pophthegm.</note> 
               <hi>Diogenes</hi> did the luxu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious ſcape-thrifts) with the Poets Lancier:
<q>
                  <l>—<note n="c" place="margin">Homer.</note> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</l>
                  <l>Fond youth, thy vitall Twist will ſoone be crackt.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>And tell them moreouer, that by their nocturnall ſuperfluities, and insatiable quaffings, they ſet but fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in Times wings, and (as a woorthy home-bred Author ſaith) ſpur but the gallopping horſe, haſten on their ſpeedy deaths, and digge their own vntime<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly graues. More haue: recourſe to Playing houſes, then to Praying houſes, where they ſet open their cares &amp; eies to ſuck vp variety of abhominations, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witching their minds with extrauagant thoughts, &amp; benumbing their ſoules with inſenſibilitie, where by fin is become ſo cuſtomarie to them, as, That to ſin, with them is deem'd no ſinne at all; conſonant to that Theologicall Maxime, <hi>Conſuetude peceandi, tol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lit peccati ſenſum;</hi> and ſemblable to <hi>Pythager as</hi> his conceite of the ſphaericall Harmony: <hi>Becauſe</hi> (ſaith
<pb facs="tcp:3736:8"/>he) <hi>we euer heare it, we neuer heare it.</hi> I will not par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularize thoſe<note n="d" place="margin">Of <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> an vnſaucuty hea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> be, in Engliſh cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Beets. <hi>Eraſm. Apoph<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thegm.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Blite a dramata</hi> (as <hi>Laberius</hi> termes another ſort) thoſe <hi>Fortune</hi>-fatted fooles, and Times I deots, whoſe garbe is the Tooth-ache of witte, the Plague-ſore of Iudgement, the Common-ſewer of Obſcaenities, and the very Traine-powder that diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chargeth the roaring <hi>Meg</hi> (not <hi>Mol</hi>) of all ſcurrile villanies vpon the Cities face; who are faine to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce blinde<note n="*" place="margin">Garlicke.</note> 
               <hi>Impudence,</hi> to perſonate himſelfe vpon their ſtage, behung with chaynes of Garlicke, as an Antidote againſt their owne infectious breaths, leſt it ſhould kill their Oyſter-crying Audience.<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Or,</hi> Tu quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que.</note> 
               <hi>Vos quoque,</hi> and you alſo, who with <hi>Scylla</hi>-barking, <hi>Sten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor</hi>-throated bellowings, flaſhchoaking ſquibbes of abſurd vanities into the noſthrils of your ſpectators; barbarouſly diuerting <hi>Nature,</hi> and defacing Gods owne image, by metamorphiſing humane<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Greenes</hi> Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boone.</note> ſhape into beſtiall forme.</p>
            <p>Thoſe alſo ſtand within the ſtroke of my penne, who were wont to <hi>Curtaine</hi> ouer their defects with knauiſh conueyances, and ſcum off the froth of all wanton vanity, to qualifie the eager appetite of their ſlapping Fauorites. In fine, theſe are the <hi>Maiſters</hi> of thoſe Mint-houſes, wherein are coyned all kinds of Atheiſticall prophanations: theſe are they, who by their wantonizing Stage-geſtures, can ingle and ſeduce men to heaue vp their heartes and affections, as a voluntary ſacrifice to that exulcerated Fiend<note n="*" place="margin">The ſpirit of Lechery.</note> 
               <hi>Aſmodeus,</hi> and all other abhominable Idoll-ſinnes, obſtinately alienating and tearing their ſelues and ſoules from the ſpirit of Grace; and by howe much
<pb facs="tcp:3736:9"/>more exact theſe are in their mimicke venerean ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, by ſo much more highly are they ſeated in the Monſter-headed <hi>Multitudes</hi> eſtimation: notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding one might thus gleeke them, (as <hi>Diagenes</hi> did the fellow that exerciſed the Play called<note n="*" place="margin">A fooliſh game vſed by louers, <hi>Eraſin. Apoph<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thegm.</hi>
               </note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) <hi>The better they doe, the more it is.</hi> Hee there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, who (by the aſsidual drinking vp the loathſome Lectures) with auaritious delectation whiffes down the muddy lees of their damnable doctrine, fals par into the pawes of the Poets tart invectiue:
<q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ridiculus tot as ſimul abſorbere placentas,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Horat. lib. 1. Sat. <hi>8.</hi>
                     </note>
                  </l>
                  <l>— In lieu of delicies,</l>
                  <l>The wit-blinde gull will ſwallow guilded Flies.</l>
               </q>
Theſe are they, whoſe exemplary laſcinious ſubiect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matter, leaue behind it (like the ſnaile) a ſlimy trackt, in which many of their Sectaries inſenſibly poſt on ſo faſt, till they plunge themſelues praecipitate into the <hi>Charybdis</hi> of incuitable deſtruction, and contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned beggery. O then let the honeſt heart lay faſt hold of the Poets counſell, who being hoode-winkt with the condenſate and cloudy night of ignorance, could by naturall inſtinct diſcerne this light,
<q>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.<note place="margin">Theognis.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Keepe and conuerſe with honeſt company,</l>
                  <l>For ſtill from them, thou mayst gleane honesty.</l>
               </q>
Could not the impetuous ſtormes bee quieted, the foaming billowes calmed, nor the ſhip preſerued,
<pb facs="tcp:3736:9"/>till <hi>Ionas</hi> was hurl'd ouer-board? Then ſurely neither can Gods wrath be qualified, nor his peſtilential ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows, which fly amongſt vs by day, &amp; lethally wound vs by night, be quiuer'd vp, till theſe <hi>Menſtruous</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Bawdy Play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers.</note> 
               <hi>Ragges</hi> be torne off (by the hand of <hi>Authority</hi>) from the Cities skirts, which ſo beſoyle and coinquinate her whole veſture. The <hi>Primum mobile</hi> which giues motion to theſe vnder-turning wheeles of wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, are (thoſe mercenary <hi>Squitter-wits</hi> miſ-called <hi>Poets,</hi> whoſe illiterate and picke-pocket Inuentions, can <hi>Emungere plebes argento,</hi> ſlily nip the bunges of the baſer troopes, and cut the reputations throat of the more eminent rank of Cittizens with corroding ſcandals: theſe are they, who by dipping their Gooſe quils in the puddle of miſchiefe, with wilde and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>collected ſpirites make them deſperately drunke, to ſtrike at the head of <hi>Nobility, Authority,</hi> and high-<hi>ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Greatneſſe.</hi> And all this they doe, but onely to purchaſe the Fee-ſimple of a Long-lane Suite, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taile a Punke in ſome new-ſtript Peticoate, and to cancell the Tauern-bill for two Bacchanall Suppers: albeit, for the whole next-enſuing quarter, they bee faine to liue by the denariall lines drawne from the Center of an Eſſex Cheeſe; and be glad ſneakingly to ſucke vp the bottomes of gameſters leauings, or young Prodigals ſuperfluities, (to whome they ſtick as faſt as a kibe to a Boyes heele) as Flies doe in ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer the drunkards ſpillings. Oh! how their teeth will ſtand wet-ſhodde at the preſence of a brace of blacke Puddings? and think themſelues as braue men as a new choſen Scauenger, if they be but prefer'd to
<pb facs="tcp:3736:10"/>the caruing vp of a two-penny Cuſtard. With re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ucrence notwithſtanding, muſt my petulant Muſe ſtoope low to thoſe wit-wonders of our age, whoſe Inuentions ſphaere moues in a myſtick orbe beyond the common Intellect. But without farther euaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, I will returne into the path of my intended pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe. Many ſet faire out-ſide colours vppon their profeſsion of Religious honeſty, but being ſtrictly lookt into by the penetrating eye of <hi>Practiſe &amp; Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance,</hi> proue ſeldome dyde in grayne. Some glit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter like <hi>Gold</hi> in their conuerſation, but put once to the touch, are found but counterfeit <hi>Alcamy:</hi> Others will needs ſeeme <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>a ſubſtantiall body,</hi> in integrity of life; but ſhaken and fiſted with the hand of <hi>Triall,</hi> become but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, an <hi>Anatomy of bones.</hi> To giue <hi>Almes</hi> is thought but a phantaſtick <hi>Ceremony,</hi> and to refreſh the comfortleſſe <hi>Lazarus,</hi> is deem'd but the maintenance of idle and exorbitant vagabonds. O where is <hi>Charity</hi> fled? Is ſhee not whipt and foyſted out of great mens Kitchins, glad to keepe ſanctuary in ſtraw-cloathd Cottages? Are not larger beneuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lences often diſtributed at the doore of one Ruſſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clad Farmer, then at ten mighty mens gates? The Magnifico's of this worlde reare vp ſumptuous buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings onely for ſhew &amp; oſtentation; whiffing more ſmoake out of their Noſes then their Chimneyes:&amp; it begets more wonder to ſee them ſhake down their bounty into the poore mans lap, then to ſee a Court Lady vnpainted, or to finde an open-fiſted Lawyer, that without a<note n="*" place="margin">Vulgarly ter med bribe.</note> 
               <hi>New-yeares guift</hi> will faithfully pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute his Clients cauſe. Notwithſtanding al this,
<pb facs="tcp:3736:10"/>ſo parcimonious are they in their domeſticke proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, that not a Rat of any good education, but ſcornes to keepe houſe with them. In thoſe Gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Times of yore, <hi>Charity</hi> was the rich mans Idoll: for they did emulate each other, in ſupplying the widdowes wants, in comforting the orphans miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and in refreſhing the trauellers wearines; and it was their earthly <hi>Sammum bonam</hi> to bee open hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and handed to each hungry ſtranger; this In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription commonly engraued vppon the front of their gates:
<q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Porta patens esto, nulli clauderis honeſto,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>O gate, ſtand ope to all, be ſhut gainſt none:</l>
               </q>
But in theſe our moderne dayes, they can cunningly tranſpoſe the poynt, and thus peruert the ſenſe:
<q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Porta patens eſto nulli, clauderis honeſto,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Stand open (Gate) to none, be ſhut gainſt all.</l>
               </q>
Doe not theſe Heauen-tempting <hi>Nimrods</hi> depopu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late &amp; leuell with the ground whole Townes, crowd and iuſtle many honeſt and ancient Farmers out of their demeſnes, deuaſtate their poſſeſſions, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe them, with their wiues, children, and families, to be Camerades with pale-fac't beggery? onely to lay the <hi>Baſis</hi> of their Babell-out-brauing Pallaces, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>billimented with Punkiſh out-ſides, to cheate the ſpeedy-approaching traueller of his hungry hopes, as <hi>Zeuxis</hi> did the ſilly Birds with his liuely-limbed Grapes: and if they bee in-lined with quaint garni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhings,
<pb facs="tcp:3736:11"/>ſhings, and coſtly furniture, and beautified with curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous-pencild peeces, whereon thy eye may glut it ſelfe by gazing, yet perhappes mayſt thou be Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>falne for want of victuals. Theſe glittering obiects are the <hi>Meduſa's</hi> that inchant, the violent inſtigati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons that ſpurre on young luxurious heires, to hurle out their angle to catch their Fathers liues, and lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhingly to long, till they ſee their moſſie bearded Sires topple vp their heeles. Neuer could the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ets triſtall ſong be better adapted, then to theſe our degenerate times:
<q>
                  <note place="margin">Ouid.</note> Filius ante diem patries inquirit in anuos.</q>
And when their Fathers ſurrender vp their breathes to him from whome it was firſt diffuſed, then do they mourne (forſooth) though ceremonially, not for that they are dead, but becauſe they dyed no ſooner.</p>
            <p>The premiſes preconſidered, what can bee ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected then but an imminent deſolation, or conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiue diſſolution of this fooliſh doting worlde, ſince vniuerſally it is but an indigeſted <hi>Châos</hi> of outragi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous enormities? <hi>Religion</hi> is made the <hi>Canopy</hi> to ſhroud the putrifaction of <hi>Hypocriſie;</hi> and its grown the higheſt Maxim <hi>in mundane policies,</hi> to <hi>ſeeme</hi> (not be) religions: equall-handed <hi>Iustice</hi> is ruſht aſide by ſtubborne <hi>Authority,</hi> and all morall <hi>Vertues,</hi> em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced in their <hi>Contraries.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How long then (moſt milde, and more merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full God) wilt thou forget to be iuſt? Oh, how long wilt thou ſhut vp the veſſelles of thy wrath, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract
<pb facs="tcp:3736:11"/>reuenge? Art thou not the powerful God of Iuſtice? howe canſt thou then bee any thing but thy ſelfe? what infinitneſſe of ſinnes are ſhot vp to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen againſt thee? yet ſtill, and ſtill, thou wooeſt vs with the humble and heauenly breath of thy holy Goſpell, vncouering thoſe vnexpreſſible woundes thou receiuedſt for our redemption, from ſinne and Sathan, that we might with pittifull commiſeration behold them: and vnceſſantly crying out vnto vs, <hi>How oft (O my deare childeren, whome I haue bought with the price of my most precious bloud) woulde I haue gathered you together, euen as an Henne doth her Chic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kins, and yet, nor yet, will you be collected?</hi> How oft hath he thundred and knockt at the doores of our hearts with the power of his ſpirit, to wake vs from the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found Ecſtaſin of Soule-killing ſinnes, yet ſtill lye wee ſnorting on the bed of Security, and cannot be rowzed? How often, O how often, hath hee out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtretched his all-ſauing hand, to heaue and helpe vs out of the ſlimy mud of our impieties, yet ſtill lye we groueling and orewhelm'd in the inſenſible Lethar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie of abhominable tranſgreſſions? How many war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning-peeces hath hee diſcharg'd vppon vs? how oft hath he diſplayed his Milke-white Enſigne of Peace vnto vs? what deuouring Plagues, what Fires, what Inundations, what vnſeaſonable Seaſons, what pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digious Births, what vnnaturall Meteors, what ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leuolent Coniunctions, what ominous Appariti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, what bloudy aſſaſſinations of mighty Kings, what Rapes, what Murthers, what fraudulencies be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt Brother and Brother? what horrible Conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racies
<pb facs="tcp:3736:12"/>by Sonnes againſt Fathers; all theſe ſent as Heralds to denounce Gods iuſt Iudgements againſt vs, yet will we not come in and be reconciled.</p>
            <p>Theſe prodigious precurſions, or precurſiue pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digies, ſhould deterre each humane creature from ſpurning againſt his Creator; theſe premonitions ſhould inſtruct vs, that Gods dreadfull vengeance waites at our doores, and like a ſtaru'd Tygar gapes for our deſtruction; and notwithſtanding he do for a while fore-ſlow to let fall his flaming rod of fierie indignation vpon vs, yet is the axe already layde to the roote of the tree, and God muſt and wil aſſured<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly come to iudgement, ſeeing that nowe, not any of thoſe ancient predictions, myſtically poynted out vnto vs in the Soule-ſauing WRIT, by the holy <hi>Prophets,</hi> remayne vnfiniſhed, but only the finall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of that Romiſh ſeuen headed <hi>Monſter,</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the recollection of the vagabundiall lewes into the ſheepe-fold of Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Doth not an vncouth terrour ſeize vpon a man, when in the depth or noone of night this ſudden &amp; vnthought-of out-cry of Fire, Fire, ſhall fill his af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frighted eares, and chaſe him out of his ſoft and qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et ſlumbers; whereat, skipping from his eaſefull bed, and diſtractedly gazing through the caſement, ſhall behold his owne houſe ore-ſpred with a bright-but<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning flame, &amp; himſelfe, together with his wife, chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, ſeruants, goods, and all, moſt lyable to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouring rapacity of imminent danger? O conſider then thou wicked man, how thy ſoule will be belea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guer'd with anguiſh &amp; horror, when in that laſt and
<pb facs="tcp:3736:12"/>terrible <hi>Day,</hi> thou ſhalt behold with thy mortall eies the Cataracts of Heauen vnſluc'd, &amp; huſhing ſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers of ſulphurious fires diſperſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues through all the corners of the earth and ayre, the whole Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe ore-canoped with a remorceleſſe flame: when thou ſhalt ſee the worldes great and glorious Iudge appeare triumphantly in the skies, whileſt mighty winged clouds of deuouring flames flye before him, as vſhers to his powerfull and terrible Maieſty; at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended with countleſſe multitudes of beauteous An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelles, golden-winged Cherubims and Seraphims ſounding their Trumpets, whoſe clamorous toungs ſhall affright the empty ayre, and call and awake the drowſie dead from their darke and dusky Cabines: when thou ſhalt ſee the diſſipated bones of all Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals ſince the Creation (concatenate &amp; knit in their proper and peculiar forme) amazedly ſtart vp, and in numberleſſe troupes flocke together, all turning vp their wondring eyes to gaze vppon their high and mighty Creator. Then, ô then will thy <hi>Conſcience</hi> recommemorate afreſh thy paſt-committed ſinnes, &amp; with the corroding ſting of guilt wil ſtab through thy perplexed ſoule; then, ô then will it be too late to wiſh the mountaines to fall vpon thee; for they themſelues for feare would ſhrinke into their cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: alas, it cannot then bee auaileable to wooe the waters to ſwallow thee; for they would bee glad to diſclaime their liquid ſubſtance and be reduced to a nullity: what will it boote thee then, to intreate the earth to entombe thee in her dankiſh wombe, when ſhe her ſelfe will ſtruggle to remoue from her locall
<pb facs="tcp:3736:13"/>reſidence, and to flye from the preſence of the great Iudge: the ayre cannot muffle thee in her foggy va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiry, for that will bee clearely refin'd with celeſtiall flames, before contaminated with humane polluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. In fine, how will thy ſoule tremblingly howle out, and break forth into bitter exclamations, when thou ſhalt heare that definitiue, or rather infinitiue ſentence denounced againſt thee, <hi>Non noui, diſeede, ito in Gehennam,</hi> I know thee not, depart, and goe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to euerlaſting torment; whileſt Legions of deuils with horride vociferations muſter about thee, like croking Rauens about ſome dead carkaſſe, wayting to carry thee. O then thou Vſurer, and thou that grindeſt the Faces of the pore, thy gold cannot ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome thee: then, thou mighty man that wrackeſt the widdow, and circumuents the orphan of his ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiue right, thy honour cannot priuiledge thee: then thou murtherer, adulterer, and blaſphemer, thy co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lourable excuſes will not purge thee: then, ô thou vncharitable churle who neuer kneweſt, that <hi>Nil di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues habet de diuitijs, niſi quod ab illo poſtulat pauper,</hi> A rich man treafures vp no more of his riches, then that hee contributes in almes: thou, that neuer im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bracedſt the counſel of that reuerend <note n="*" place="margin">Ambroſe.</note> Father, who cryes, <hi>Paſce fame morientem: quiſquis paſcendo ſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re poteris: ſi non paucris, fame occidisti:</hi> Feed him that dyes for hunger, whoſoeuer thou art that canſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue and wilt not, thou ſtandeſt guilty of famiſhing: then I ſay, in that day ſhalt thou pine in perdition: then, ô thou luxurious Epicure, that through the fiue ſenſes, which are the Cinque-ports, or rather ſinne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports
<pb facs="tcp:3736:13"/>of thy ſoule, gulpeſt downe delightfull ſinne, like water, they will be to thee like the Angels booke, ſweet in thy mouth, but bitter in thy bowels: then, ô thou (gorbellied Mammoniſt) that piles vp and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſteth huge maſſes of refulgent earth, purchaſed by all vnconſcionable courſes, yet carieſt nothing with thee, <hi>Niſiparna quod vrna capit,</hi> but a Coffin and a Winding-ſheet; thy faire pretences will bee like characters drawne vpon the ſands, or arrowes ſhot vp to heauen-ward, they cannot releaſe thee from Satans inexpiable ſeruitude: Then, ô thou Canker<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worme of Common-wealths, thou monſter of man, thou that putteſt out the eye of Iuſtice with bribes, or ſo cloſely ſhuts it, that the clamorous cry of the poore mans caſe cannot open it; thou that makeſt the Lawe a noſe of waxe to turne and faſhion it to thine owne priuate end, to the vtter diſgrace of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcionable Iuſtice, and to the lamentable ſubuerſion of many an honeſt and vpright cauſe, thy <hi>quirkes,</hi> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latorie <hi>demurres, conueyances</hi> and <hi>conniuences</hi> cannot acquit thee: but thou ſhalt bee remooued with the Writ <hi>Corpus cum cauſa,</hi> into the loweſt and darkeſt dungcon of damnation. No, no, the Lord of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen and earth (who is good in infinitneſſe, and infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nit in goodneſſe) will winnow, garble, and ſanne his corne, the choyce wheate hee will treaſure vp in the garners of eternall felicity, but the chaffe and darnell muſt be burnt with vnquenchable fire: There muſt you languiſh in torments vnrelaxable: there muſt you frie and fieeze in one ſelfe-furnace: there muſt you liue in implacable and tenebrous fire which (as
<pb facs="tcp:3736:14"/>
               <note n="2" place="margin">Auguſt. de ciu. t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dei.</note> 
               <hi>Auſtin</hi> defines) ſhall giue no light to comfort you. Then will you wiſh (though then too late) that you had beene created loathſome Toades, or abhorred Serpents, that your miſeries might haue clos'd vp with your liues: but you muſt be dying perpetually, yet neuer dye; and (which enuirons mee with a trembling terror) when you haue languiſht in vnex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſible agonies, tortures, gnaſhings, and horrid howlings ten thouſand millions of yeares, yet ſhall you be as far from the end of your torments, as you were at the beginning. A confuſed modell &amp; mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty figure of hell haue wee conglomerate in our fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, drowſily dreaming that it is a place vnder earth, vnceſſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly (Aetna-like) vomiting ſulphurious flames, but we neuer purſue the meditation thereof ſo cloſe as to conſider what a thing it is to liue there eternal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: for this adiunct <hi>Eternall</hi> intimates ſuch infinite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, as neither thought can attract or ſuppoſition apprehend:and further to amplifie it with the words of a woorthy writer: Though all the men that euer haue or ſhal be created, were (<hi>Briareus</hi> like) hundred-handed, and ſhoulde all at once take pennes in their hundred hands, and ſhould doe nothing elſe in ten hundred thouſand millions of yeares but ſumme vp in figures as many hundred thouſand millions as they could, yet neuer could they reduce to a totall, or confine within number, this tri-ſillabled word <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Can any Chriſtian then (vpon due conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on hereof) forbeare to proſtrate himſelfe with flexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble humility before the glorious throne of grace, &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:3736:14"/>there with flouds of vnfained teares, repentantly ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iure and diſclaime the allurements of carnal corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the painted pleaſures of the world, and the bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter-ſweetneſſe of ſinne, which is the deaths-wound of his ſoule: for <hi>Peccatum in animo, quaſi vulnus in corpore,</hi> a weapon wounds the body, and ſinne the ſoule: for what profits it a man to winne the whole worlde, and looſe his owne ſoule: The ſoundeſt me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod therefore to preuent our excluſion from the throne of Gods mercy is to imagine we ſtill ſee him in his Iuſtice preſent, whatſoeuer or whenſoeuer we intend or attempt any blacke deſeigne; let vs but ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umbragiouſly fancy (as one hath it) the firmament to be his face, the all-ſeeing Sunne his right eye, the Moone his left, the winds the breath of his Noſtrels, the Lightning and Tempeſts, the troubled action of his ire, the Froſt and Snow his frownes, that the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen is his Throne, the earth his Foot-ſtoole; that he is all in all things, that his omnipreſence filles all the vacuities of heauen, earth, and ſea: that by his power hee can vngirdle and let looſe the ſeas impetuous waues, to ore-whelme and bury this lower Vniuerſe in their vaſt wombes in a moment: that hee can let drop the blew Canopy (which hath nothing aboue it whereto it is perpendicularly knit) or hurle thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der-bolts through the tumerous cloudes, to paſh vs praecipitate through the center into the loweſt dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geon of hell. Theſe alluſiue cogitations of Gods omnipotent maieſty wil curb in and ſnafflle vs from ruſhing into damnable actions, if we vnremouably ſeate them in our memories.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:3736:15"/>
            <p>Make then a couenant with thine eies and heart ô man, leaſt they doate on earthly droſſe, ſurfet on the ſugred pils of poyſonous vanities, and ſo inſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly hurle downe thy better part into the gulph of ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reuocable damnation: if not for thy ſelfe ſake, yet iniure not thy <hi>Creator,</hi> who hath drawne thee by his owne <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or Patterne, moulded thee in his owne forme, and to make thee eternally happy, hath infus'd his own eſſence into thee. For thy Soule (by the<note n="*" place="margin">Ariſtotle.</note> Philoſophers confeſſion) is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>an Infuſion Celeſtiall,</hi> no Natural traduction: and in that reſpect,<note n="*" place="margin">Philo.</note> another calles it <hi>Coeli apopaſma,</hi> an arrach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or cantell puld from the Celeſtiall ſubſtance, which cannot terminate it ſelfe within a lumpe of fleſh; euen as the beames of the Sun, though they touch the earth, and giue life to theſe inferior crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, yet ſtill reſide in the body of the Sun, whence they are darted: ſo thy Soule, though it be ſeated ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther within the filme of the brain, or confined in the center of the heart, and conuerſeth with the Senſes: yet, <hi>Haeret origini ſuae,</hi> (ſayeth<note n="*" place="margin">Seneca.</note> one) <hi>It will still there haue being, whence it hath its beginning.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Remember then thy Creator in the dayes of thy youth; call vpon him, while it is called to day, opor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunely: for as the Poet no leſſe ſweetly, then diſcreet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſung:
<q>
                  <l>Quis ſcit, <note place="margin">Horat. lib. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. Ode. <hi>7.</hi>
                     </note> an adijciant hodiernae crastina ſummae</l>
                  <l>Tempora di ſuperi?</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Who knowes ore-night, that he next morne ſhall breath?</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:3736:15"/>
            <p>Then take Dauids <hi>Manè,</hi> early in the morne, not the deuils <hi>Mane,</hi> ſtay till to morrow: for thou knoweſt hee will bring thee to iudgement, yet thou knoweſt not when, nor in what yeare, nor in what moneth of the yeare, nor in what weeke of the moneth, nor in what day of the weeke, nor in what houre of the day, nor in what minute of the houre, nor in what mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of that minute: for hee will come <hi>Sicut fur in nocte,</hi> like a theefe in the night, ſuddenly, before with a winke thou canſt locke vp thine eie, or in thy brain create the nimbleſt thought. Canſt thou then hope to ſtand iuſtified in thy Makers preſence, when thou haſt cram'd the diuell with thy ſap of ſtrength, and full-gorg'd him with the pureſt acorne-maſt of thy ſinowey virility, if at laſt thou come limping on Times tottering crouches, to preſent vnto him the offall, huskes, and moroſity of thy doating decrepite age? What thank it is to pardon our enemies when we cannot hurt them? to giue away our goods whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we can enioy them no longer? to abandon our plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, when we cannot vſe them? to forſake ſin, when it bids farewell to vs? and at laſt only to ſurceaſe to offend, when ability of offending is taken from vs? No, no, he will then paralell thee with the ſluggard, that neuer wold acquire food till he was firſt ſtaru'd, and ranke thee with the ſottiſh Ideot, that could not learn to know a fiſh, till he was already ſtung with a Scorpion: thy palſey-ſhaken praiers wil be like <hi>Cains</hi> oblation, vnacceptable to the Lord and noyſome to his noſthrils. Thinkſt thou to expiate Gods Iuſtice when thou haſt prodigally ſweal'd out the blazing
<pb facs="tcp:3736:16"/>lampe of thy brighteſt daies in the diuels Chappel, if at laſt thou come creeping (when thy breath lyes twinkling in the ſocket of thy noſthrilles) to ſet it vp in Gods Sanctuary, hoping then and there to hane it repleniſht with his all-ſauing Grace and Mercy? O mocke not thy ſoule with theſe deluding Phan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſma's: for as<note n="a" place="margin">Plut. in. vit. Alex.</note> 
               <hi>Alexander</hi> ſeeing one of his ſouldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers whetting his dart, when others his fellowes went forth to fight, caſhierd him, ſaying, <hi>Inutilis acte, qui pararet arma tune cum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s vtendum,</hi> he's vnfit to beare armes that ha's them to make ready when he ſhould skirmiſh: ſo will God ſend thee packing (as he did the fooliſh virgins) with this retorſion; Thou comſt disfurniſht with no oyle in thy lampe, and thou de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſern'ſt no mercy, that neuer deſirdſt it till now in mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery.</p>
            <p>Gather thy ſelfe betimes then, within the wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons of Faith, Hope, Charity, Repentance, and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeuerance, and let Prayer ſtand perpetuall Sentinel: for if the diuell once get footing within thee, he will hardly bee eiected, ſo wily is hee in peruenting thee, that thou canſt not bee too wary in preuenting him. For as<note n="b" place="margin">Plutark.</note> 
               <hi>Iphicrates</hi> anſwered his Generall (who asked him, why hee ſurrounded his ſouldiours with a wall, when there was no feare of foe-mens approach) <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundans cautela non nocet,</hi> A man cannot be too pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uident in preuenting obuious and occurrent dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers: ſo canſt thou not be too cautelous in repelling the perillous ſtratagems of the diuels aſſaults; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore may I cloſe vp the precedencie, with that wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy ſaving of a more worthy<note n="*" place="margin">Owen. Epigr.</note> Epigrammatiſt,
<pb facs="tcp:3736:16"/>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Nemo cauenda timet, qui metuenda canet.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>No man needs feare, that feares before he needs.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>O cleanſe and purifie thy heart then by earneſt prayer and powerfull eiaculations, which is made the loathſome cage of ſinne, the ſilent receptacle of all diabolicall cogitations, and the diſmall dungeon of malignant motions; that the Spirit of grace may there finde harbour, and take delight to be thy In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate. Remember, ô thou mighty man, that ſwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling titles of Honor are but <hi>folia vanitatis,</hi> the leaues of vanity, a Gnathonicall puffe, and a blaſt of the chaps: Remember, ô thou rich man, that terrene &amp; tranſitory pleaſures are like the Bee, though they yeeld hony, yet carry they a ſting, and are but <hi>Lilia terrae,</hi> more delectable in ſhew, then durable incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance: Remember, ô thou Extortioner, thou cruell man, thou murtherer, thou adulterer, thou de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfull man, thou that vnconſcionably detaineſt the hirelings wages, and thou that acteſt inexorable vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lanies ſecretly in the darlie, impriſoned from the worldes dull eye; that if the Eagle can diſcerne, <hi>Sub frutice Leporem, ſub fluctibus piſcem</hi> (as<note n="c" place="margin">Auguſtm.</note> one hath it) the Hare vnder the buſh<hi rend="sup">o</hi>, and the Fiſh vnder the waues; much more can God, who is the Creator of creatures, penetrate the cloſet of thy hart with his all-ſeeing eye, and diſcerne thy clandeſtine ſinnefull practiſes, before, and in their very conception, and for them he will bring thee to iudgement. Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, ô thou that ſwayſt the ſword of Iuſtice, to ſtrike
<pb facs="tcp:3736:17"/>or ſaue, as thou art ſuggeſted by thine owne endes, profites, or affections, that though thy couert pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects bee not envulgar'd to the worlds generall eye, yet a day of Reuelation will come, that <hi>Nihil occul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum quod non reuelabitur,</hi> when all thy partiall and priuate practiſes ſhall bee ſtript, euiſcerate and laide as apparantly open, as the Sheepe vppon the gam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brell. But now with reuerence, and Doue-like hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility, to you (which are Iehouahs <hi>Embaſſadors,</hi> the <hi>Light</hi> of the world, and <hi>Salt</hi> of the earth,) doe I ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſe my ſpeech, muſtred vp in the meaneſt &amp; mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt ranke of words: O I could wiſh, that all of you ſtood without the liſt of that reprehenſion of vices, which once an ancient and honeſt<note n="a" place="margin">Guil. Malm. de Pont ficibus.</note> Hiſtorian twit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the Monkes of <hi>Canterbury</hi> with: <hi>Monachi Cantu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>artenſes</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>ſecularibus haud abſimiles erant, ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num curſibus auocari: aui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m praedam raptu aliorumque valucrum per mane ſequi: ſpumantis equi tergum pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mere: teſſer as quatere, &amp;c.</hi> Some riſe earely in the morning to ſee their hounds purſue the prey, but not to pray: ſome delight to catch foules, but not ſoules: ſome take pleaſure to caſt a Dye wel, but not caſt to die well. Doth the wilde Aſſe bray, ſaith <hi>Iob,</hi> when he hath graſſe, or loweth the Oxe when he hath fod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der? but I dare not ſay, no more doe ſome of you preach when you haue once got a Benefice. If there bee any that entertaine Religion with their Lord, preach the praiſe of their Patrons; Preachers in the Pulpits, chatters in their chambers, ſuiting their lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſey-woolſey profeſſions with their ſeuerall ends; O let thoſe remember how God met with a miſchiefe
<pb facs="tcp:3736:17"/>that notorious<note n="*" place="margin">Caſsiodorus, lib <hi>12.</hi> cap. <hi>4.</hi> Nicephoru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. lib. <hi>14.</hi> cap. <hi>31.</hi>
               </note> Neſtorius, who, for his tempori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing inconſtancie ſet wormes a worke to eat out his tongue: O let them looke into the ſtory of one <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cebolus</hi> a<note n="*" place="margin">Socrat. Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partit. l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>b. cap. <hi>38.</hi>
               </note> Sophiſter, who accommodating his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſsion to the faſhions of the Emperors, fained him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in the dayes of <hi>Constantius,</hi> to bee a moſt fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent Chriſtian; But when <hi>Iulian</hi> the Apoſtata was ruler, preſently hee turn'd Paynime, and in his orati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons proclaim'd <hi>Iulian</hi> a God; and when <hi>Iulian</hi> was dead, in <hi>Iouinians</hi> time, hee would haue turn'd backe to Chriſtianity; whereupon, for his mutability and lightnes in his Religion, his horrid conſcience draue him to the Church gates, &amp; there hurling himſelfe flat, cried and bellowed with a lowd voice, <hi>Conculca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te me ſal infatuatum;</hi> trample mee vnder your feete, vnſauoury ſalt that I am, entirely wiſhing out of his ſoules agony, that he had neuer ſeene the light, or<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t his Conception his tongue had beene riuetted to the roofe of his mouth.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, and indefinitly to all, remember ſo to liue, as you ſtil may be prepar'd for the ſtab of death: then will you deſire to ſing your <hi>Requiem,</hi> and <hi>Quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſque Demine?</hi> longing to be diſſolued and to ſleepe in peace, recluſiuely from the turbulent ſea of earthy carefull miſeries; diſcerning clearely by the ſpiritual eye of vnderſtanding, that mans life is a wayfare, and a warfare; a wayfare, becauſe it is ſhort, and a warre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare, for that it is ſharpe; and that worldly delightes are deceitefull, and of no durability; like the water<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerpent <hi rend="sup">d</hi> 
               <hi>Ephemeron, ſimu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> oritur, moritur,</hi> no ſooner
<pb facs="tcp:3736:18"/>bred, but dead: collecting likewiſe out of humane experience, that the beſt life, is but a weary and tedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous pilgrimage, and feeles no touch of true ſolace, till at the euening of his dayes, he lodge at the Inne of death; for Death is the path to Life, a Gaole-de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuery of the Soule, a perfect health, the hauen of heauen, the finall victory of terreſtriall troubles, an eternall ſleepe, a diſſolution of the body, a terror to the rich, a deſire of the poore, a pilgrimage vncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, a theefe of men, a ſhadow of life, a reſt from trauell, an epilogue to vaine delight, a conſumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of idle deſires, a ſcourge for euill, a guerdon for good; it disburdens vs of all care, vnmannicles and frees vs from vexation, ſolicitude, &amp; ſorrow. Of all thoſe numberleſſe numbers that are dead, neuer any one returned to complaine of Death, but of thoſe few that liue, moſt complaine of Life: on earth <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo ſuâ ſorte conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tus,</hi> euery man grumbles at his beſt eſtate. The very Elements whereby our <hi>Ens</hi> (as the ſecondarie cauſe) is preſeru'd, conſpire againſt vs: the fire burnes vs, the water drowns vs, the earth an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noyes vs, and the aire infects vs: our daies are labo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, our nights comfortleſſe: the heate ſcorcheth vs, the cold benumbs vs: health ſwels vs with Pride, ſicknes empaleth our beauties; friends turne Swal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes, they will ſing with vs in the Sommer of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity, out in the Winter of trial, they wil take wing and bee gone: Enemies brand our reputations with deprauing imputations; and the enuious man hur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth abroad his grins to enſnare our liues: who wold then deſire to liue where there is nothing that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gets
<pb facs="tcp:3736:18"/>content? For this world is a Theater of vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, a <hi>Chaos</hi> of confuſions, an Embaſſadour of miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe, a tyrant to vertue, a breaker of peace, a fauo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite of warre, a ſweet of vices, a coyner of lyes, an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uile of Nouelties, a table of Epicuriſme, a furnace of luſt, a pitte fall to the rich, a burthen to the poore, a Cell of Pilgrims, a denne of Theeues, a calumniator of the good, a renowner of the wicked, a cunning impoſtor, and a deceiuer of all.</p>
            <p>How is the progreſſe of poore-proud-mans life violently agitated (like the riuer <hi>Eurypus</hi>) with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarious motions? The pleaſure of the wily world thus inueagles him, <hi>Veni ad me, ego reficiam,</hi> Come vnto me and I will drowne thee in delight: the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption of the luxurious fleſh thus ingles him, <hi>Veni ad me, ego inficiam,</hi> Come vnto mee, and I will infect thee, the diuell hee whiſpers this in his eare, <hi>veni ad me, ego decipiam,</hi> Come vnto mee, and I will cheate and deceiue thee: but our ſweet and ſacred Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt, with perſwaſiue inducements, thus in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treates him, <hi>Veni <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 words">
                     <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ad me, ego retipiam,</hi> Come vnto me (I pray thee) that are heauy laden, and I will receiue, and exonerate thee, and with the mighty arme of my mercy and compaſsion, lift off that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſupportable loade, which cruſheth downe to hel thy groaning ſoule.</p>
            <p>Study then to liue, as dead to the world, that thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maiſt liue with God: for the iuſt man is ſaide, <hi>nun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam, ſed poſt mortem viuere,</hi> neuer to liue till after death. Indeauor thy ſelfe to march faire through this worlds labyrinth: not to ſquander and looke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſquint
<pb facs="tcp:3736:19"/>vppon the <hi>Cyrcean</hi> allurements thereof: but without turning either to the right or left hand, run ſtraight on in that Eclipiticke line, which will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct thee to that Celeſtiall Ieruſalem, where (with that immaculate Lambe Chriſt Ieſus) thou ſhalt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy, pleaſure without paine, wealth without want, reſt without labour, ioy without griefe, and immen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiue felicity without end. Therefore I will bind vp the premiſes with this concluſiue exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Apoſtles, <hi>Repent, and amend your lines,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 4.17.</note> 
               <hi>for the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God is at hand.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:3736:19"/>
            <head>Proh dolor! hinc Lachrymae.</head>
            <l>FAire <hi>Honor</hi> footes it: ſquallid <hi>Glo-wormes</hi> ride,</l>
            <l>And dart <hi>falſe ſplendors</hi> from vnpaid-for <hi>Pride:</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Ith beſt Religion true, none truely knowes;</l>
            <l>In ſuch deform'd conformity ſhe goes.</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Luſt's</hi> a tyr'd Iade, and waits for whome will mounther</l>
            <l>The Lord with's Landreſſe, Counteſſe, with Page encounter.</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Hymen,</hi> tread out thy torch; <hi>Plate's</hi> conceſsion,</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Omnia communia,</hi> is the C profeſſion.</l>
            <l>Full beames of <hi>Grace</hi> beguild th'obſequious <hi>Groome,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>VVho'l kiſſe the ground with's knee: But there's no roome</l>
            <l>For high-borne <hi>Merit:</hi> he ith ſhadow ſtands,</l>
            <l>Farre out o'th Margent of great-baſe <hi>Commands:</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Sleeke <hi>Flatteries</hi> cups repleniſh't to the brim:</l>
            <l>But ſwolne <hi>Promotion</hi> lookes aſquint on him,</l>
            <l>VVho hoards more <hi>treaſures</hi> in's volumnious braine,</l>
            <l>Then all thoſe earth-bred <hi>ſtars, Prides</hi> gawdy traine.</l>
            <l>Peace, moyſt-ey'd Muſe, thy beſt Inuentions poore,</l>
            <l>Thy <hi>Toung's</hi> portculliſt, but thy thoughts ſpeake more.</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:3736:20"/>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:3736:20"/>
            <head>The Authors Character.</head>
            <l>IN hope of guerdonile Epiſtle none: with</l>
            <l>
               <hi>O my thrice honour'd Lord, your worth alone, &amp;c.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Nor blow the bellowes to <hi>Ambitions</hi> fire:</l>
            <l>With Eaglet-ayres make <hi>Butterflies</hi> mount higher</l>
            <l>Then their owne Nat'ral pitch:nor with fil'd phraſe,</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Baſe-temperd Birth,</hi> will burniſh, ſcowre, or glaze:</l>
            <l>No <hi>Popiniey</hi> ſhall weare <hi>worths</hi> liuerie,</l>
            <l>Emblaz'd with word-embroderie by me.</l>
            <l>Let <hi>Enuies</hi> wombe be my eternall graue,</l>
            <l>If I turne <hi>Sycophant,</hi> or vnſeaſon'd ſlaue:</l>
            <l>To furniſh <hi>ſpangled-Fooles</hi> with what they want:</l>
            <l>Make th' <hi>Aſſe</hi> beleeue he carries th'<hi>Elephant,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Craule int'a <hi>Great-mans</hi> boſome by ſome icaſt,</l>
            <l>Like a ſtaru'd Lowſe vpon a Taylors breaſt;</l>
            <l>Or cloath the fatall ſtrumpet <hi>Helena,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>With th'attributes of chaſt <hi>Andromeda:</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Nor ſquint I after <hi>praiſe,</hi> or <hi>plauſiue grace:</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>Mans honest plainneſse needs feare no mans face.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>Inſta, non magna vole.</hi>
            </l>
            <pb facs="tcp:3736:21"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3736:21"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
